Guide to the Isabella Graham Foster Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Isabella Graham Foster papers
1883-1907
MS 220
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(8 boxes)
The papers consist almost entirely of Isabella G. Foster's correspondence and reflects her life as the daughter of well-to-do parents in New Haven, her career as a student at Vassar College, from which she graduated in 1899, and her teaching experiences in the New Haven public schools and at a seminary in Pennsylvania.
Foster, Isabella Graham, d. 1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Florence Hoadley.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Isabelle Graham Foster Collection emcompasses eight manuscript boxes; the majority is correspondence to Miss Foster from personal friends. The collection covers letters, postal cards, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous items–such as play programs. The dates of the collection are January 1883-1907, inclusive.
The Foster Manuscripts could be of value for information on New Haven, Connecticut, and Vassar College. Miss Foster's home was on Orange Street where she resided with her parents, Mr. and Mrs. Harry W. Foster. Mr. Foster was a merchant who operated H.W. Foster and Company, carpets and curtain materials, at 48 Orange Street. From the content of Isabella's letters, the Foster family moved in the upper social circles of New Haven.
Isabella attended Vassar College sporadically due to illness caused by extensive studies. Although her graduation date was not discussed in the letters, the date was probably in 1899. She later taught in New Haven Public Schools and at a seminary in Pennsylvania. Her major was apparently the Classics, Latin and Greek.
Among the newspaper clippings is an article of particular interest which states that Anita Hemming, an outstanding and beloved member of the class of 1897 of Vassar College, was a Negro. She was allowed to graduate from Vassar. The story is covered in an article filed for March 22, 1897 "How a Negro Slipped Through Vassar College." The newspaper stories, other than the numerous society columns, are listed on a following register page.
As a reference work, the Isabelle Graham Foster manuscripts are of value for New Haven, Connecticut and Vassar College.
Biographical / Historical
Isabella Graham Foster: educator; graduated from Vassar College, 1899; studied at Yale and the University of Chicago; taught English and classics in the New Haven public schools and at a seminary in Pennsylvania.
Students; Upper class; Women -- Education; Women; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social life and customs; Postcards; Educators; Women teachers; Foster, Isabella Graham, d. 1955; Vassar College
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1883 -1894 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1895-1896 September (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1896 October-1897 November (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1897 March-November (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1897 December-1898 October (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1898 November-1899 November (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1899 December-1907, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Postal Cards, undated (Box 8, Folder 1 - 8)
    - Programs, undated (Box 8)
    - Calling cards and invitations, undated (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Statement regarding a residence on Elm Street, owned by an Edwards family and not to be sold, November 4, 1895 (Box 8)
    - Article concerning Yale students not being hopeless offenders of the law, December 15, 1895 (Box 8)
    - "Too Happy to Be Still," a demonstrative celebration for McKinley in New Haven, November 3, 1896 (Box 8)
    - Opening of a tea room at the New Haven Woman's Exchange, December 14, 1896 (Box 8)
    - "Long Service on the Bench," information on Judge Elisha Carpenter, January 31, 1897 (Box 8)
    - Mrs. Hattie Chapin, a minister's wife, kills herself and her lover in Falls Village, Connecticut, February 21, 1897 (Box 8)
    - Dr. Frank T. Budd sued Miss Lina Phipps, May 11, 1897 (Box 8)
    - "Let All Render Thanks," Thanksgiving proclamation of President Cleveland, July 31, 1897 (Box 8)
    - Congressman Hartman of Montana offers an amendment to the Indian Appropriation Bill, July 31, 1897 (Box 8)
    - "How a Negro Girl Slipped Through Vassar College," the story of Anita Hemming, August 22, 1897 (Box 8)
    - "Pupils Leave High School," students leave Hillhouse as parents consider overcrowded conditions injurious to their health, March 15, 1899 (Box 8)
    - "Dr. Douglas Receives Call," the resignation of the Reverend George William Douglas as rector of Trinity Crhuch to become "special preacher" at Grace Church, New York, February 19, 1900 (Box 8)
    - Vassar Will Not Teach Cooking, President Taylor thinks out of place in college course - wants to put women on same intellectual plane as men, undated (Box 8)
    - "In a Padded Cell," concerning heirs of House of Wittelsbach, Otto and brother, Ludwig, of Bavaria, undated (Box 8)
    - "Miss Bartlett's New Book," historical sketches of New Haven, as, New Haven Green, a church, Grove Street Cemetary, Hillhouse Avenue, John Trumbull, etc., undated (Box 8)
    - "Every Day Use of English," by Professor Palmer of Harvard, undated (Box 8)
    - Review of Barbarine, a book by Alice Bently Twitchell, undated (Box 8)
    - "Impressions of Rome," letter concerning Rome visit by Mrs. Alice Twitchell, undated (Box 8)
    - "Loss by Fire of '50,000'," Bowditch Furniture Company burned out on Orange Street, undated (Box 8)
    - "Opening of Davenport," a hotel at corner of Orange and Court Streets, undated (Box 8)
    - "Thomas R. Trowbridge Dead," account of death of owner of largest shipping firm in New England, undated (Box 8)